Abigail Polin, PhD

Carnegie Observatories 813 Santa Barbara Street Pasadena, CA 91101

 $abigail@caltech.edu\\ abigailpolin.com\\$

I am a joint postdoctoral research fellow sharing a Burke fellowship in theoretical physics at Caltech and a Carnegie fellowship at Carnegie Observatories. I employ a combination of analytic, numerical and high-performance computing techniques to study the physics driving astrophysical explosions and I specialize in connecting that theory to observed transient phenomena.

EDUCATION

Ph.D. in Physics

May 2020

University of California, Berkeley

Advisors: Peter Nugent & Daniel Kasen

Thesis: Pushing the Helium Envelope: Signatures of Normal and Unusual Supernovae from Sub-Chandrasekhar Mass White Dwarf Explosions

M.S. in Physics

May 2015

University of California, Berkeley

B.S. in Physics

December 2012

New York University

RESEARCH APPOINTMENTS

Joint Postdoctoral Research Fellow

2020-Present

Carnegie Fellowship, Carnegie Observatories Burke Fellowship in Theoretical Physics, Caltech

NSF Graduate Research Fellow

2015-2020

University of California, Berkeley

Fellowships & Awards

	NERSC Early Career Award: High Impact Scientific Achievement	2021
	Burke Fellowship in Theoretical Physics, Caltech	2020-Present
	Carnegie Fellowship, Carnegie Observatories	2020-Present
I	NSF Graduate Research Fellowship	2015-2020
AD	Wonderfest Science Envoy	2019-2020
GR.	Berkeley Connect Fellowship	2014-2016
1	Outstanding Graduate Student Instructor Award, UC Berkeley	2014

Publication Summary

(see end of CV for complete publication history)

19 journal articles: 7 identifying supernovae belonging to a newly discovered class of transients, which matched our modeled theoretical predictions

Abigail E. Polin

Computing Grants (PI-ED)

National Energy Research Scientific Computing Center (NERS) ERCAP 2022:	,
Perlmutter GPUs Cori KNL CPUs	,
NERSC Early Career Award 2021: Early Access to the Perlmutt	er GPU Supercomputer
NSF Extreme Science and Engineering Discovery Environment	(XSEDE):
XRAC 2021: Stampede2 CPUs	, ,
DOE INCITE Leadership Computing Award 2023 (co-PI):	
Oak Ridge National Laboratory, Summit GPUs Oak Ridge National Laboratory, Frontier CPUs Argonne National Laboratory, Polaris GPUs	$\dots 300,000$ node-hours
Awarded Telescope Time (PI-ed)	
Las Campanas Observatory:	
Magellan: Baade 6.5m telescope — IMACS Optical & FIRE NIR Spectrographs	nights (2022B) nights (2022A)
Invited Talks & Conference Proceedings:	
SuperVirtual 2022 - From Common to Exotic Transients University of Delaware, Physics and Astronomy Colloquium Chandra Workshop: Supernova Remnants and Their Progenitors NBIA Workshop Radiation Transfer in Astrophysics, Niels Bohr Institute Lawrence Berkeley National Lab, NERSC Awards Seminar Series UC Davis, Physics & Astronomy Seminar Purdue University, Astronomy Seminar Florida State University, Astronomy Seminar Stony Brook University, Astronomy Seminar Harvard University, Galaxy and Cosmology Seminar Northwestern University, Observational Astronomy Seminar UC Santa Barbara, Astronomy Lunch Talk UC Santa Cruz, Astronomy FLASH Talk Caltech, Astronomy Tea Talk Carnegie Observatories, Lunch Talk Haverford College, Physics and Astronomy Colloquium UC Santa Cruz, Pre-Filippenkopalooza Supernovae Meeting KITP, UC Santa Barbara, ZTF Theory Network Summer Meeting Weizmann Institute of Science, Particle Physics and Astrophysics Worksl New York University, CCPP Astrophysics Seminar University of Wisconsin, Milwaukee, Astronomy Seminar	Nov 2021 Apr 2021 Feb 2021 Nov 2020 Oct 2020 Dec 2019 Nov 2019 Oct 2019 Oct 2019 Oct 2019 Oct 2019 Sept 2019 Aug 2018 Aug 2018

Abigail E. Polin

	KITP White Dwarfs Conference, Santa Barbara, CA	Nov 2022
3UTED —	NASA TDAMM Workshop, Anapolis, MD	$\mathrm{Aug}\ 2022$
	AAS Dissertation Talk, Winter Meeting, Honolulu, HI	Jan 2020
	Midwest Workshop on Supernovae and Transients, Ohio State	Sept 2019
RIBU	The Beginnings and Ends of Double White Dwarfs, DARK, Copenhagen	July 2019
ONT	UC Berkeley, Theoretical Astrophysics Seminar	Jan 2018
00	Supernovae: The LSST Revolution Workshop, Northwestern	May 2017
	APS March Meeting, Baltimore, MD	Mar 2013
ı	APS March Meeting, Houston TX	Mar 2011

MENTORSHIP: ADVISING STUDENT RESEARCH

GRADUATE STUDENTS

Peter Scherbak (Caltech)

Margot Fitz Axen (UT Austin, DOE CSGF Fellow)

Undergraduate Students

Desiree Harvell (CASSI Summer Student: California State University, San Bernardino)

Siddharth Boyeneni (Caltech SURF: Caltech)

Hayden Campos (CASSI Summer Student: Dartmouth)

Wynn Jacobson-Galán (UCSC, now graduate student at UC Berkeley)

TEACHING EXPERIENCE

ADJUNCT INSTRUCTOR (UC Berkeley) Astro 9: Introduction to Scientific Computing Sole Instructor: in charge of syllabus design and instruction HEAD GRADUATE STUDENT INSTRUCTOR (UC Berkeley) Physics 7A: Introductory Mechanics GRADUATE STUDENT INSTRUCTOR (UC Berkeley) Astro C10: Introduction to General Astronomy Fall 2019 Astro 7A: Introduction to Astrophysics Fall 2017 Astro 250: Introduction to High Performance Computing Physics 7A: Introductory Mechanics ADJUNCT INSTRUCTOR (New York University) Observational Astronomy UC BERKELEY TEACHING CONFERENCE Developer and instructor of a mandatory workshop for first time graduate student instructors COURSEWORK IN TEACHING DEVELOPMENT (UC Berkeley) Physics 198: Progressive Physics Education Spring 2014 Physics 375: Professional Preparation in Teaching Physics Fall 2013	Outstanding Graduate Student Instructor Award (UC Berkeley)	2014
Head Graduate Student Instructor (UC Berkeley) Physics 7A: Introductory Mechanics Graduate Student Instructor (UC Berkeley) Astro C10: Introduction to General Astronomy Astro 7A: Introduction to Astrophysics Fall 2019 Astro 250: Introduction to High Performance Computing Physics 7A: Introductory Mechanics Adjunct Instructor (New York University) Observational Astronomy UC Berkeley Teaching Conference Developer and instructor of a mandatory workshop for first time graduate student instructors Coursework in Teaching Development (UC Berkeley) Physics 198: Progressive Physics Education Physics 198: Physics Pedagogy Seminar Spring 2014	Adjunct Instructor (UC Berkeley)	
Physics 7A: Introductory Mechanics GRADUATE STUDENT INSTRUCTOR (UC Berkeley) Astro C10: Introduction to General Astronomy Astro 7A: Introduction to Astrophysics Astro 250: Introduction to High Performance Computing Physics 7A: Introductory Mechanics ADJUNCT INSTRUCTOR (New York University) Observational Astronomy Spring 2013 UC BERKELEY TEACHING CONFERENCE Developer and instructor of a mandatory workshop for first time graduate student instructors COURSEWORK IN TEACHING DEVELOPMENT (UC Berkeley) Physics 198: Progressive Physics Education Physics 198: Physics Pedagogy Seminar Spring 2014	Astro 9: Introduction to Scientific Computing Sole Instructor: in charge of syllabus design and instruction	Summer 2020
GRADUATE STUDENT INSTRUCTOR (UC Berkeley) Astro C10: Introduction to General Astronomy Astro 7A: Introduction to Astrophysics Fall 2017 Astro 250: Introduction to High Performance Computing Physics 7A: Introductory Mechanics Fall 2013 ADJUNCT INSTRUCTOR (New York University) Observational Astronomy Spring 2013 UC BERKELEY TEACHING CONFERENCE Developer and instructor of a mandatory workshop for first time graduate student instructors COURSEWORK IN TEACHING DEVELOPMENT (UC Berkeley) Physics 198: Progressive Physics Education Physics 198: Physics Pedagogy Seminar Spring 2014	HEAD GRADUATE STUDENT INSTRUCTOR (UC Berkeley)	
Astro C10: Introduction to General Astronomy Astro 7A: Introduction to Astrophysics Astro 250: Introduction to High Performance Computing Physics 7A: Introductory Mechanics ADJUNCT INSTRUCTOR (New York University) Observational Astronomy Spring 2013 UC Berkeley Teaching Conference Developer and instructor of a mandatory workshop for first time graduate student instructors Coursework in Teaching Development (UC Berkeley) Physics 198: Progressive Physics Education Physics 198: Physics Pedagogy Seminar Fall 2019 Fall 2017 Fall 2017 Spring 2013	Physics 7A: Introductory Mechanics	Spring 2014
Astro 7A: Introduction to Astrophysics Astro 250: Introduction to High Performance Computing Physics 7A: Introductory Mechanics ADJUNCT INSTRUCTOR (New York University) Observational Astronomy Spring 2013 UC BERKELEY TEACHING CONFERENCE Developer and instructor of a mandatory workshop for first time graduate student instructors COURSEWORK IN TEACHING DEVELOPMENT (UC Berkeley) Physics 198: Progressive Physics Education Physics 198: Physics Pedagogy Seminar Fall 2014 Spring 2015 Physics 198: Physics Pedagogy Seminar	Graduate Student Instructor (UC Berkeley)	
Astro 250: Introduction to High Performance Computing Physics 7A: Introductory Mechanics ADJUNCT INSTRUCTOR (New York University) Observational Astronomy Spring 2013 UC Berkeley Teaching Conference Developer and instructor of a mandatory workshop for first time graduate student instructors COURSEWORK IN TEACHING DEVELOPMENT (UC Berkeley) Physics 198: Progressive Physics Education Physics 198: Physics Pedagogy Seminar Spring 2014	Astro C10: Introduction to General Astronomy	Fall 2019
Physics 7A: Introductory Mechanics ADJUNCT INSTRUCTOR (New York University) Observational Astronomy UC BERKELEY TEACHING CONFERENCE Developer and instructor of a mandatory workshop for first time graduate student instructors COURSEWORK IN TEACHING DEVELOPMENT (UC Berkeley) Physics 198: Progressive Physics Education Physics 198: Pedagogy Seminar Spring 2014	Astro 7A: Introduction to Astrophysics	Fall 2017
ADJUNCT INSTRUCTOR (New York University) Observational Astronomy UC Berkeley Teaching Conference Developer and instructor of a mandatory workshop for first time graduate student instructors Coursework in Teaching Development (UC Berkeley) Physics 198: Progressive Physics Education Spring 2015 Physics 198: Physics Pedagogy Seminar Spring 2014	Astro 250: Introduction to High Performance Computing	Spring 2017
Observational Astronomy UC BERKELEY TEACHING CONFERENCE Developer and instructor of a mandatory workshop for first time graduate student instructors COURSEWORK IN TEACHING DEVELOPMENT (UC Berkeley) Physics 198: Progressive Physics Education Spring 2015 Physics 198: Physics Pedagogy Seminar Spring 2014	Physics 7A: Introductory Mechanics	Fall 2013
UC BERKELEY TEACHING CONFERENCE Developer and instructor of a mandatory workshop for first time graduate student instructors COURSEWORK IN TEACHING DEVELOPMENT (UC Berkeley) Physics 198: Progressive Physics Education Spring 2015 Physics 198: Physics Pedagogy Seminar Spring 2014	Adjunct Instructor (New York University)	
Developer and instructor of a mandatory workshop for first time graduate student instructors Coursework in Teaching Development (UC Berkeley) Physics 198: Progressive Physics Education Spring 2015 Physics 198: Physics Pedagogy Seminar Spring 2014	Observational Astronomy	Spring 2013
for first time graduate student instructors Coursework in Teaching Development (UC Berkeley) Physics 198: Progressive Physics Education Physics 198: Physics Pedagogy Seminar Spring 2014	UC BERKELEY TEACHING CONFERENCE	
COURSEWORK IN TEACHING DEVELOPMENT (UC Berkeley) Physics 198: Progressive Physics Education Physics 198: Physics Pedagogy Seminar Spring 2014	Developer and instructor of a mandatory workshop	Fall 2014
Physics 198: Progressive Physics Education Spring 2015 Physics 198: Physics Pedagogy Seminar Spring 2014	for first time graduate student instructors	
Physics 198: Physics Pedagogy Seminar Spring 2014	Coursework in Teaching Development (UC Berkeley)	
	Physics 198: Progressive Physics Education	Spring 2015
Physics 375: Professional Preparation in Teaching Physics Fall 2013	Physics 198: Physics Pedagogy Seminar	Spring 2014
	Physics 375: Professional Preparation in Teaching Physics	Fall 2013

Abiqail E. Polin 4

LEADERSHIP, OUTREACH & SERVICE

Public Talks

Carnegie Astronomy Lecture Series, Huntington Library, Pasadena CA	May 2023
AAS Journal Author Series	Jan 2023
Astronomy on Tap, Pasadena CA	Oct 2022
Wonderfest Science Series, Virtual Talk	Jan 2021
Radio Interview: Women in STEM w/ KPOO-FM	Mar 2020
Wonderfest Science Envoy Speaks at the Verdi Club, San Francisco, CA	Feb 2020
Berkeley Art Museum and Pacific Film Archive, Berkeley, CA	Nov 2018

Leadership & Service Positions

Carnegie Postdoc Representative	2021-2023

Caltech TAPIR Seminar Organizer 2021-2023

CASSI Science Mentor

2021-2022

CASSI is a 10 week internship and educational program at Carnegie designed to improve undergraduate students' fluency with research and communication.

Wonderfest Science Envoy

2019-2020

A program funded by the Gordon and Betty Moore Foundation that identifies PhD students who show particular science-popularization promise. The program helps us to develop the subtle art and science of public outreach. The program's participants emerge as articulate Science Envoys.

UC Berkeley Society for Women in the Physical Sciences:

v v	v	
Astronomy Coordinator		Fall 2015 - Spring 2019
Mentoring Coordinator		Fall 2014 - Spring 2016

Berkeley Connect Fellow

Fall 2014 - Spring 2017

Berkeley Connect is a teaching and mentorship program intended to strengthen the relationship between undergraduate students and the Physics Department. As a Fellow, I contributed to curriculum design, led class meetings, and mentored students one-on-one.

Respect is Part of Research: Founding Member and Peer Facilitator 2014 - 2016 RPR is a graduate student group that runs annual peer-led sexual assault and sexual harassment prevention workshops for incoming first-year graduate students. RPR's primary mission is to create a respectful, positive working environment where everyone can do their best science.

Compass Program Organizer/Instructor/Research Mentor Summer 2014 The Berkeley Compass Project is a Physics graduate student-run organization that aims to improve the experiences of undergraduate students from under-represented groups interested in STEM.

Anonymous Peer Reviewer for: ApJ, ApJL & MNRAS

Abiqail E. Polin 5

Publications [ADS Link]

Summary: 19 journal articles, 3 as first author, 7 identifying supernovae belonging to a newly discovered class of transients, which matched our modeled theoretical predictions

1. Using Anisotropies as a Forensic Tool for Decoding Supernova Remnants **Polin, A.**, P. Duffell, and D. Milisavljevic

The Astrophysical Journal Letters 940, L28, (2022).

2. Nebular Models of Sub-Chandrasekhar Mass Type Ia Supernovae: Clues to the Origin of Ca-rich Transients

Polin, A., P. E. Nugent, and D. Kasen

The Astrophysical Journal, 906, 65 (2021).

3. Observational Predictions for Sub-Chandrasekhar Mass Explosions: Further Evidence for Multiple Progenitor Systems for Type Ia Supernovae

Polin, A., P. E. Nugent, and D. Kasen

The Astrophysical Journal, 873, 84 (2019).

4. SN 2020jgb: A Peculiar Type Ia Supernova Triggered by a Massive Helium-Shell Detonation in a Star-Forming Galaxy

Liu, C., A. Miller, A. Polin, and 25 colleagues.

arXiv:2209.04463. accepted/in press The Astrophysical Journal (2023).

Fast and Not-so-Furious: Case Study of the Fast and Faint Type IIb SN 2021bxu
Desai, D., and 38 colleagues including A. Polin.
arXiv:2303.13581. submitted to MNRAS. (2023).

6. SN 2021zny: an early flux excess combined with late-time oxygen emission suggests a double white dwarf merger event

Dimitriadis, G., and 30 colleagues including A. Polin.

MNRAS, 521, 1. (2023).

 SN 2016dsg: A Thermonuclear Explosion Involving a Thick Helium Shell Dong, Y., S. Valenti, A. Polin, and 29 colleagues. The Astrophysical Journal, 934, 2, (2022).

8. The origin and evolution of the normal Type Ia SN 2018aoz with infant-phase reddening and excess emission

Qi Ni, Y., D. Moon, M. Drout, **A. Polin**, and 40 colleagues arXiv:2206.12437, *submitted to* The Astrophysical Journal (2022).

9. The Absolute Magnitudes of 1991T-like Supernovae Phillips, M., and 22 colleagues including A. Polin. The Astrophysical Journal, 938, 47, (2022).

10. Physical Properties of the Host Galaxies of Ca-rich Transients Dong, Y., D. Milisavljevic, and 9 colleagues, including **A. Polin** The Astrophysical Journal, 927, 2, (2022).

11. Infant-phase Reddening by Surface Fe-peak Elements in a Normal Type Ia Supernova Qi Ni, Y., D. Moon, M. Drout, A. Polin, and 40 colleagues Nature Astronomy, cover article February, (2022).

Abigail E. Polin

12. The Zwicky Transient Facility Census of the Local Universe I: Systematic search for Calcium rich gap transients reveal three related spectroscopic sub-classes

De, Kishalay, and 49 colleagues including A. Polin

The Astrophysical Journal, 905, 58 (2020).

13. ZTF Early Observations of Type Ia Supernovae. III. Early-time Colors As a Test for Explosion Models and Multiple Populations

Bulla, M. and 24 colleagues including A. Polin

The Astrophysical Journal, 902, 1, 48 (2020).

14. Strong Calcium Emission Indicates that the Ultraviolet-flashing SN Ia 2019yvq Was the Result of a Sub-Chandrasekhar Mass Double-detonation Explosion

Siebert, M. R.; G. Dimitriadis, A. Polin, and R. J. Foley

The Astrophysical Journal Letters, 900, 2, L27, (2020).

 The Spectacular Ultraviolet Flash from the Peculiar Type Ia Supernova 2019yvq Miller, A. A., M. R. Magee, A. Polin, and 42 colleagues The Astrophysical Journal, 898, 1, 56 (2020).

16. Ca hnk: The Calcium-rich Transient Supernova 2016hnk from a Helium Shell Detonation of a Sub-Chandrasekhar White Dwarf

Jacobson-Galán, W., A. Polin, R. J. Foley, and 11 colleagues

The Astrophysical Journal, 896, 2, 165 (2020).

17. ZTF 18aaqeasu (SN 2018byg): A Massive Helium-shell Double Detonation on a Sub-Chandrasekhar Mass White Dwarf

De, K., M. Kasliwal, A. Polin, and 27 colleagues

The Astrophysical Journal Letters, 873, L18 (2019).

18. K2 Observations of SN 2018oh Reveal a Two-Component Rising Light Curve for a Type Ia Supernova

Dimitriadis G., R. J. Foley, A. Rest, D. Kasen, A. L. Piro, A. Polin, and 144 colleagues The Astrophysical Journal Letters, 870L, 1D (2019).

19. Gravitational Wave Hotspots: Ranking Potential Locations of Single-Source Gravitational Wave Emission

Simon J., A. Polin, A. Lommen, B. Stappers, L.S. Finn, F. Jenet and B. Christy The Astrophysical Journal, 784, 60 (2014).